{
  "reference_number": "1492",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Climate change is seriously affecting our country and the world, specifically as we are an island nation and have many island\n neighbours. We should set a 2050 in the legislation so that the government can be held accountable to the courts to reach that\n\n target"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Ideally, we should set a Net Zero Emmissions target, but I think that is unrealistic given our reliance on the dairy industry. Instead, we\n should adapt - seek to revitalise and diversity our economy using innovation, alongside reducing reliance on the dairy industry, while\n\n mitigating the impact of the diary industry by stablising short-lived gases"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should not rely on emissions reductions from overseas - it is important in this area to be independent"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Target should be certain and stable - as a central tenet of the rule of law. We should be ambitious and realistic and not allow for\n minimising our committments if we are not close to meeting them."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is good that the budget period (5 years) does not directly overlap with the electoral terms. This requires more interparty\n cooperation in the House when budgets are set, as any party could become accountable for that budget when they come into office\n in a later electoral term. This would insulate the policy-making process from short term political pressures"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Naturally, but this could be done in a state of emergency, rather than giving the Govt specific ability to review the second budget\nwithin the Zero Carbon Act."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission's recommending power should mirror that of the Law Commission's. It should have advisory power,\n\nwith mechanisms to hold Govt to account, but should not be able to make delegated-legislation as it is neither part of government\nnor an elected official body. The factors that the Commission should consider are good ones, including Treaty obligations."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Govt should table the Commission's recommendations and issue a public report on it, perhaps comparable to tabling of UN\nHuman Rights reports and responses."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1. Maori interests and the Treaty of Waitangi 2. Dairy industry 3. Meeting our Paris obligations 4. What NZ will do in response to\npotential climate refugees coming from the Pacific"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation and Mitigation should go hand in hand Resilience of our communities is already at issue, with major floods, tornadoes etc,\n\nand with biosecurity threats challenging our agricultural security and conservation efforts."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Share information on their exposure to climate change risks + share information on how they will meet their carbon budgets"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "#climatejustice!"
    }
  ]
}
